<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>SheffieldR</title>
<link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/</link>
<atom:link href="https://SheffieldR.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Shefffield R User Group</description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.26</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 12:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>SheffieldR : November 2025 Meetup</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2025-11/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Most of the year has passed without much activity but we are pleased to announce that Dr Robert Smith and Oliver Dolin have volunteered to talk about their development of a web platform for healthcare professionals.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/54764888522_1269a889a5_k.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/slackline/54764888522/">Taking Time to Reflect by Neil Shephard</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="where-and-when" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="where-and-when">Where and When</h2>
<p>Meeting will be held 2025-11-19 17:30-19:00 in Lecture Theatre 8 of <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/relation/16098200">The Diamond</a>.</p>
<p>Sign up via <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sheffieldr-sheffield-r-users-group/events/306236464/">Meetup</a> although remote attendance is possible via <a href="https://meet.google.com/sns-yqak-nhy">Google Meet</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Access to healthcare-professional administered medicines in England varies significantly across the country, resulting in inequitable health outcomes. Our interactive web platform identifies optimal new care site locations. It uses a greedy search method outlined in Schneider &amp; Smith (2020) to rank candidate sites that maximize a range of user-selected objective functions such as: travel distance, travel time, adherence or health outcomes. Users can customize input parameters like travel cost and CO<sub>2</sub>/km, and estimate the impact of adding new sites on a range of outcomes including patient travel time, adherence, health outcomes, CO<sub>2</sub> emissions, and out-of-pocket costs. The platform uses data on the socioeconomic and demographic structure of each Lower Super Output Area, a small community of around 1500 individuals, in England. It combines this with information on the prevalence of disease, and the relationship between geographic access and outcomes. It allows users to assess the impact of creating one or more of the sites identified on national and regional outcomes, and to assess the impact on inequalities. The platform is in beta stage, and we are interested in feedback from the research community on how to build upon this work going forward.</p>
</section>
<section id="bios" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bios">Bios</h2>
<p>Oliver Dolin is a data scientist at <a href="https://darkpeakanalytics.com/">Dark Peak Analytics</a>, where he builds web interfaces for health economic models in R Shiny. He has contributed to R packages for Health Economics and Outcomes Research (HEOR) tasks (<a href="https://github.com/dark-peak-analytics/assertHE">assertHE</a>, and an internal package for network meta-analysis plot visualizations). He holds an MSc in Health Data Science from London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine and a BA in Experimental Psychology from the University of Oxford.</p>
<p>Robert Smith is a Director of Health Economics at <a href="https://darkpeakanalytics.com/">Dark Peak Analytics</a>. He leads the development of health economic models, web-platforms and software for Health Economic Evaluation. He is co-director of the R for Health Technology Assessment consortium. Rob has previously advised on projects for the WHO, CGD, 10 Downing St, UKHSA and most of the top 10 pharma companies. He has a PhD in Public Health Economics &amp; Decision Science from the University of Sheffield.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2025-11/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/54764888522_1269a889a5_k.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SheffieldR : March 2025 Meetup</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2025-03/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We’ve been a bit quiet recently but are back with our first meetup of 2025 on 13th March where we welcome <a href="https://www.sheffield.ac.uk/smph/people/clinical-medicine/neil-lawrence">Dr Neil Lawrence</a> and <a href="https://www.sheffield.ac.uk/smph/people/population-health/charlotte-head">Charlotte Head</a> from the University of Sheffield School of Medicine and Population Health.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/54027972058_1fa30a254a_h.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/slackline/54027972058/">Histograms by Neil Shephard</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="where-and-when" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="where-and-when">Where and When</h2>
<p>Meeting will be held 2025-03-13 12:30-13:30 in Room 315 of <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/relation/16098200">The Diamond</a>.</p>
<p>Sign up via <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sheffieldr-sheffield-r-users-group/events/306236464/">Meetup</a> although remote attendance is possible via <a href="https://meet.google.com/bhv-xmkk-gjk">Google Meet</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="charlotte-head---devtools" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="charlotte-head---devtools">Charlotte Head - <code>{devtools}</code></h2>
<p>Want to make your R life easier? This talk introduces how to build R packages (it’s much easier than you think!) and how they can organise your code. Using <a href="https://devtools.r-lib.org/"><code>devtools</code></a>, we’ll build a simple package (by getting some ASCII animals to compliment you using the R packages <code>praise</code> and <code>cowsay</code>!). We’ll be covering the essentials: structure, functions, and documentation. By the end, you’ll be ready to create your own packages. Bring your laptop if you’d like to follow along (the download prerequisites for codealongs are the <code>devtools</code>, <code>praise</code> and <code>cowsay</code> packages, as well as Rtools (Windows) or XCode (Mac)).</p>
<section id="bio" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bio">Bio</h3>
<p>Charlotte is a Research Associate in Public Health Economic Modelling working on the <a href="https://www.phiuk.org/local-health-global-profits">Local Health and Global Profits project</a> since September 2024. Beginning with a Biomedical Science degree at Sheffield Hallam University and spending some time working with the Clinical Microbiology team at Doncaster Royal Infirmary, she then moved on to the University of York for postgraduate research in Antimicrobial Resistance where she found a love for coding in R and big data. She has a strong interest in public health and data science, especially the use of big data to inform health decision-making and the implementation of One-Health policies and commercial determinants of health. Charlotte is currently working on generating local synthetic populations using the Health Survey for England for use in public health policy and is open to suggestions for how best to validate these at low geographies.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1mJhN_dDBC3SrZVn2ZvlY2jSrvG6jR_VsfXY-cMIhwFI/edit#slide=id.p">An Introduction to R Packages | Charlotte Head</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="neil-lawrence---sitar-longitudinal-multilevel-modelling" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="neil-lawrence---sitar-longitudinal-multilevel-modelling">Neil Lawrence - SITAR : Longitudinal multilevel modelling</h2>
<p>Super Imposition by Translation And Rotation (SITAR) is an advanced statistical modelling that uses longitudinal multilevel modelling to appropriately summarise time series data, particularly useful for modelling the growth of children. Advantages include application to data that is measured at variable frequencies, as well as relatively simple model fit statistics that help the selection of hyperparameters and the avoidance of overfitting. However, the use of terms such as ‘random effects’, akin to terms like ‘missing at random’ when considering challenges around missing data, create barriers when explaining these models to clinicians. Technical challenges such as the impact of time varying covariates also make robust estimation of the impact of treatment changes within patients difficult to define. This talk will show the application of SITAR modelling to cohort and registry data and some of the insights that have been gained, and hopefully inspire conversation about how such modelling can move from being purely descriptive, to predictive and suitable to be incorporated into clinical decision support tools on the front line of clinical practice.</p>
<!-- markdownlint-disable-next-line MD024 -->
<section id="bio-1" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bio-1">Bio</h3>
<p>Neil is an NIHR doctoral research fellow in paediatrics and child health, and clinically works as a paediatric registrar. Originally having studied Civil Engineering, Neil completed a degree in medicine and then the NIHR academic foundation programme. He completed the National Medical Director’s Clinical Fellow Scheme working for NHS Digital within the Data, Insights &amp; Statistics division, where he developed his interest in data analytics using R. He is working to gain insights from real world data within the International Congenital Adrenal Hyperplasia Registry, amongst other data sets including those related to COVID-19, as well as cohort data from the neonatal unit at Jessops Wing. Neil is keen to develop his interest in clinical decision support tools, and is always happy to hear suggestions about how to best explain findings from statistical models to other clinicians, as well as effective ways to incorporate statistical modelling within software as a medical device in an explainable and transparent fashion.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1REuMD5B-r_Uyy9xl5gInzsDWMiEVmowi/edit#slide=id.p1">SITAR modelling of growth in preterm infants and the effect of antenatal steroids</a></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2025-03/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 12:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/54027972058_1fa30a254a_h.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SheffieldR : Hacktoberfest 2024</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-10/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We kick off this semester’s Sheffield R User Group meetings in October with a series of hackathons to participate in <a href="https://hacktoberfest.com/">Hacktoberfest 2024</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-10/img/DO-HFest-EmailBanner-600px-2-@2x.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Hacktoberfest 2024</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Hacktoberfest is an annual “<em>month-long celebration of all things open-source</em>” that runs across <a href="https://github.com">GitHub</a> and <a href="https://gitlab.com">GitLab</a> which “<em>welcome[s] anyone who is interested in diving in, and everyone who’s already part of the open-source software community.</em>”. These sessions are open to all regardless of your skill level and experience with writing R code, documentation or using <a href="https://git-scm.com/">Git</a>, <a href="https://github.com">GitHub</a> or <a href="https://gitlab.com">GitLab</a>.</p>
<p>We have planned four meetings across the month of October to help and support each other in contributing to open-source projects related to the <a href="https://www.r-project.org/">R</a> language and ecosystem including <a href="https://ropensci.org/">rOpenSci</a> and <a href="https://www.bioconductor.org/">Bioconductor</a>. In the first session on Friday 2024-10-04 we will go over the basics of Git and contributing via <a href="https://github.com">GitHub</a>/<a href="https://gitlab.com">GitLab</a> to open-source projects and how to go about finding R projects with issues that you could tackle and solve as part of Hacktoberfest 2024.</p>
<p>The remaining sessions will be held weekly on Fridays at lunch time from 12:30-13:30 in the University of Sheffield’s Students Union. During these sessions you can come along and seek support and offer help to those who have questions, whether that is with some aspect of R, documentation, continuous integration, linting, tests or anything you have been working on as part of Hacktoberfest.</p>
<section id="schedule" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="schedule">Schedule</h2>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;"><strong>Date/Time</strong></th>
<th><strong>Venue</strong></th>
<th><strong>Google Meet</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://calendar.google.com/calendar/event?action=TEMPLATE&amp;tmeid=MzFhcW0zZnBwOWI3Mm52c3JoMnFzcjU3Mm4gbi5zaGVwaGFyZEBzaGVmZmllbGQuYWMudWs&amp;tmsrc=n.shephard%40sheffield.ac.uk">2024-10-04 17:00-18:30</a></td>
<td>Blue Room G22 Computer Science, Regents Court</td>
<td><a href="https://meet.google.com/pjo-rskm-ktk" class="uri">https://meet.google.com/pjo-rskm-ktk</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://calendar.google.com/calendar/event?action=TEMPLATE&amp;tmeid=M2VrcHI0cXZhNGt2cjlhZGlydTVhcDdia2NfMjAyNDEwMTFUMTEzMDAwWiBuLnNoZXBoYXJkQHNoZWZmaWVsZC5hYy51aw&amp;tmsrc=n.shephard%40sheffield.ac.uk&amp;scp=ALL">2024-10-11 12:30-13:30</a></td>
<td>VR4 Meeting Room, University of Sheffield Students Union</td>
<td><a href="https://meet.google.com/yjs-psie-vjh" class="uri">https://meet.google.com/yjs-psie-vjh</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://calendar.google.com/calendar/event?action=TEMPLATE&amp;tmeid=M2VrcHI0cXZhNGt2cjlhZGlydTVhcDdia2NfMjAyNDEwMTFUMTEzMDAwWiBuLnNoZXBoYXJkQHNoZWZmaWVsZC5hYy51aw&amp;tmsrc=n.shephard%40sheffield.ac.uk&amp;scp=ALL">2024-10-18 12:30-13:30</a></td>
<td>VR4 Meeting Room, University of Sheffield Students Union</td>
<td><a href="https://meet.google.com/yjs-psie-vjh" class="uri">https://meet.google.com/yjs-psie-vjh</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://calendar.google.com/calendar/event?action=TEMPLATE&amp;tmeid=M2VrcHI0cXZhNGt2cjlhZGlydTVhcDdia2NfMjAyNDEwMTFUMTEzMDAwWiBuLnNoZXBoYXJkQHNoZWZmaWVsZC5hYy51aw&amp;tmsrc=n.shephard%40sheffield.ac.uk&amp;scp=ALL">2024-10-25 12:30-13:30</a></td>
<td>VR5 Meeting Room, University of Sheffield Students Union</td>
<td><a href="https://meet.google.com/yjs-psie-vjh" class="uri">https://meet.google.com/yjs-psie-vjh</a></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="preparation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="preparation">Preparation</h2>
<p>To participate you will need a <a href="https://github.com">GitHub</a> and/or a <a href="https://gitlab.com">GitLab</a> account and to register between 2024-09-23 and 2024-10-31 on the <a href="https://hacktoberfest.com/participation/">Hacktoberfest site</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="learn-more" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="learn-more">Learn More</h2>
<p>There are a bunch of resources available at <a href="https://hacktoberfest.com/participation/#beginner-resources">Resources for Beginners</a> if you are unfamiliar with <a href="https://git-scm.com/">Git</a> or <a href="https://github.com">GitHub</a>/<a href="https://gitlab.com">GitLab</a> but these aren’t essential as we are aiming to cover the basics and help you over the course of these events.</p>
<p>If you are interested in making contributions to R core - the code and documentation that gets distributed as base R - check out the information from <a href="https://contributor.r-project.org/">R Contributor Site</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-10/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-10/img/DO-HFest-EmailBanner-600px-2-@2x.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="86" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SheffieldR : June 2024 Meetup</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-06-21-june-meetup/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This month, we’re shaking things up with an exciting line-up of lightning talks presented by you, our vibrant community members! This is your chance to share your knowledge, showcase your projects, and discuss your favourite R topics in a quick, 5-10 minute format.</p>
<p>If you have a fascinating R project you’re working on, a useful package you can’t live without, or a data analysis technique you think others should know about <a href="https://forms.gle/YSWXarhwUpXZQp2J6">sign up</a> to present a lightning talk and share it with the SheffieldR community!</p>
<p>Whether you’re a seasoned R user or just starting out, we encourage everyone to participate. This is a fantastic opportunity to learn from each other, exchange ideas, and inspire fellow R enthusiasts.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-06-21-june-meetup/image.png" title="Lightning Talks" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Lightning Talks</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>How to Participate:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Register Your Topic: Fill out <a href="https://forms.gle/YSWXarhwUpXZQp2J6">this form</a> to register your lightning talk topic.</p></li>
<li><p>Prepare Your Talk: Visual aids are welcome but not required.</p></li>
<li><p>Engage and Enjoy: Join us on the day, share your insights, and enjoy learning from others.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>After the event, join us for drinks at the <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/way/178278884">The University Arms pub</a>, it’s a great opportunity to continue the conversation, network, and relax with fellow R enthusiasts.</p>
<p>Meeting is on Friday 21st of June at 4:00-5:30 in Seminar Room DB07 (42) <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/relation/16555061">Bartolome House</a>, Broomhall, Sheffield S3 7RH</p>
<p>Sign up <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sheffieldr-sheffield-r-users-group/events/301279273/">here</a>.</p>
<p>Remote attendance is possible using <a href="http://meet.google.com/gwr-anoz-mas">Google Meet</a>.</p>
<p>If you have any questions or inquiries please email us <a href="mailto:sheffieldr@sheffield.ac.uk">sheffieldr@sheffield.ac.uk</a>.</p>
<!--more-->
<section id="topics-covered" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="topics-covered">Topics Covered</h2>
<p>A few links to material from some of the talks given…</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/erikaris/rplaywright">rplaywright - Erika Siregar</a> - Erika has developed a wrapper for the <a href="https://playwright.dev/">playwright</a> testing framework and is keen to receive feedback from those who are able to test it.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/EmmaPritchard/Detecting_changes_population_trends">Detecting Changes in Population Trends - Emma Pritchard</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/sophie-a-lee">Sophie Lee</a> talked about using Quarto to create accessible, engaging teaching material.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/Ben-L-Stats/BITsurv">BITSurv R Package for survival analysis - Ben</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/simonrolph/render-rmarkdown-with-actions">Render R Markdown with GitHub Actions - Simon Rolph</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://blog.nshephard.dev/sheffieldr-fabricatr-20240621/">No Data, No Worries : Fabricatr</a></p></li>
</ul>
<p>Erika Siregar also floated the idea of establishing a local Sheffield <a href="https://rladies.org/">R Ladies</a> chapter so if anyone is keen and would like to be involved in that please reach out and contact <a href="emsiregar1@sheffield.ac.uk">Erika directly</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-06-21-june-meetup/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-06-21-june-meetup/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="62" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SheffieldR : April 2024 Meetup</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-04-22-april-meetup/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Join us for the April edition of SheffieldR User Group, where we continue to explore the exciting world of R programming and its applications. This month, we’re thrilled to feature two insightful talks from experts in the field.</p>
<p>Our first speaker, Daniel Brady, will delve into the intricacies of profiling and code optimization in R. Discover how to streamline your code for improved efficiency and performance, as Dan shares practical tips and techniques to enhance your programming skills.</p>
<p>Following Dan’s presentation, we’ll hear from Joe Heffer, who will introduce us to strategies used in R while implementing a pipeline. Dive into the world of health data as Joe walks us through packaging, ensuring data integrity, and handling sensitive data securely through the development and implementation of a pipeline.</p>
<p>Meeting is 2024-04-22 12:00-1:30 in <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/relation/16201517">Regent Court</a>, John Pemberton LT B (40). Sign up <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sheffieldr-sheffield-r-users-group/events/300164087/">here</a>. Remote attendance is possible using <a href="https://meet.google.com/xka-dxah-sqf">Google Meet</a>.</p>
<p>If you have any questions or enquiries please email us <a href="mailto:sheffieldr@sheffield.ac.uk">sheffieldr@sheffield.ac.uk</a>.</p>
<!--more-->
<section id="profiling-and-optimising-your-r-code" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="profiling-and-optimising-your-r-code">Profiling and optimising your R code</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-04-22-april-meetup/image.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Profiling</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Nobody likes slow code, luckily most programming languages provide you with tools to help you analyse and enhance your code’s performance and R is no exception.</p>
<p>In this session we’ll cover some of the tools and strategies available in the R ecosystem to optimise your code. We’ll start by giving a brief introduction to profiling, and then we’ll use the <a href="https://rstudio.github.io/profvis/"><code>{profvis}</code></a> to profile some code to determine which parts are taking up the most execution time. Then we’ll move on to discuss potential strategies that reduce execution time, and we’ll use the <a href="https://bench.r-lib.org/"><code>{bench}</code></a> to compare these different strategies against one another to find the best performing solution.</p>
<section id="biography---daniel-brady" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="biography---daniel-brady">Biography - Daniel Brady</h3>
<p><a href="https://rse.shef.ac.uk/contact/dan-brady/">Dr Daniel Brady</a> is a Research Software Engineer in the RSE team at the University of Sheffield. His background is in Cognitive Neuroscience, completing his PhD at Goldsmiths in 2016. Since then he has worked as a Research Fellow at Birkbeck and the University of Surrey and as Research Technician at the University of Reading. He has experience of writing research software and analysis pipelines using R, Python and Julia. He is also a keen advocate of open and reproducible research practices.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="r-strategies-for-health-data-pipelines" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="r-strategies-for-health-data-pipelines">R Strategies for Health Data Pipelines</h2>
<p>In this session, we delve into the intricate world of health data. Our discussion encompasses crucial aspects such as data packaging, ensuring data integrity, and handling sensitive health data securely.</p>
<p>Navigating the complexities of health data, we address the challenges associated with the arrival of unforeseen data volumes. With a focus on scalability, we examine techniques to handle unexpectedly large data sets using packages like <a href="https://arrow.apache.org/docs/r/"><code>{arrow}</code></a> and <a href="https://duckdb.org/docs/api/r.html"><code>{DuckDB}</code></a> and <a href="https://dplyr.tidyverse.org/"><code>{dplyr}</code></a>.</p>
<section id="biography---joe-heffer" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="biography---joe-heffer">Biography - Joe Heffer</h3>
<p>Dr Joe Heffer is a Research Data Engineer at the University of Sheffield where he has worked on various project across the University. He actively assists researchers in leveraging data engineering techniques to uncover insights and drive impactful research outcomes. Additionally, Joe advocates for best practices and fosters an open community of collaboration among researchers and data professionals.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-04-22-april-meetup/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2024 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-04-22-april-meetup/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SheffieldR : Bring your Data and Code</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-03-21/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This March meetup see’s a slight deviation from the normal format of the SheffieldR meetups as we are inviting you to bring your data, code, R knowledge and enthusiasm along to help each other out in a “Hackathon” style meeting.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://the-turing-way.netlify.app/_images/communication.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>This illustration is created by Scriberia with The Turing Way community. Used under a CC-BY 4.0 licence. DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3332807">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3332807</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Meeting is 2024-03-21 17:30-19:00 in the <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/way/174114141">Portobello Centre</a>, Seminar Room C02 B (just off Mappin Street). Sign up is via <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sheffieldr-sheffield-r-users-group/events/299525846/">Meetup</a>. Unfortunately we won’t be running remote attendance this time because of the nature of the meeting.</p>
<p>If you have any questions or enquiries please email us <a href="mailto:sheffieldr@sheffield.ac.uk">sheffieldr@sheffield.ac.uk</a>.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Maybe you’ve a problem using <a href="https://rstudio.github.io/renv/articles/renv.html">renv</a> to manage your packages or you’re stuck with a particular data wrangling problem or haven’t worked out the perfect layout of your graph then bring your data and code along and see if there is someone who can help you solve your problem. Whether that is using the <a href="https://www.tidyverse.org">Tidyverse</a>, <a href="https://rdatatable.gitlab.io/data.table/">data.table</a>, <a href="https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org">ggplot2</a> or base graphics.</p>
<p>Obviously we’ll need people with experience to come and help others solve their problems, but even if you’re just starting out on your R journey you will know something to contribute.</p>
<p>If you’d like to come along we’ve setup a short <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSffiI7o68QcFngrirJ7YrjGgJfduwtv0UWJDQeNQLLKUDQmzA/viewform?pli=1">form</a> for you to indicate what areas you are looking for assistance with or can help others with.</p>
<section id="reprex" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reprex">Reprex</h2>
<p>Its possible that the section of code you are having trouble with is part of a larger workflow. To make it easier for people to understand the problem and offer assistance it would be beneficial if you are able to abstract out the problem to what is know as a Minimal “<em>Reproducible Example</em>” often shortened to the portmanteau “<em>reprex</em>”. There is advice on <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/help/minimal-reproducible-example">How to create a Minimal, Reproducible Example</a> on Stack Overflow and there is also the R package <a href="https://reprex.tidyverse.org/">{reprex}</a> which helps “<em>prepare reproducible example code via the clipboard</em>”.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-security-and-sensitivity" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-security-and-sensitivity">Data Security and Sensitivity</h2>
<p>If your problem involves sensitive data then please be mindful of this. See the University of Sheffield <a href="https://infosecurity.shef.ac.uk/training_courses/online/protecting-research-data">Information Security Training</a> pages, in particular the training on <em>Protecting Research Data</em>, <em>Protecting Personal Data</em> and <em>Protecting Information</em>. If you are not a student or member of staff at The University of Sheffield please refer to your institution or employers guidelines on data security.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-03-21/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://the-turing-way.netlify.app/_images/communication.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SheffieldR : February 2024 Meetup</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-02-15/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Apologies for the short notice but thanks to Simon Rolph, who has <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfjbSGzIHs71YCxD_2knDg126q7m0ywFwF7rspqyVpmZolxpg/viewform">volunteered to give a talk</a>, we have scheduled a meeting for February.</p>
<p>Meeting is 2024-02-15 17:30-19:00 in Hicks Building LT9. Sign up via <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sheffieldr-sheffield-r-users-group/events/299095698/">Meetup</a>. Remote attendance is possible using <a href="https://meet.google.com/ahi-irru-rvx">Google Meet</a>.</p>
<p>If you have any questions or enquiries please email us <a href="mailto:sheffieldr@sheffield.ac.uk">sheffieldr@sheffield.ac.uk</a>.</p>
<!--more-->
<section id="dive-into-targets" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dive-into-targets">Dive into <a href="https://books.ropensci.org/targets">{targets}</a></h2>
<p>Delve into the dynamic world of the <a href="https://books.ropensci.org/targets">{targets}</a> R package—a powerful tool designed to streamline and enhance your data science and analysis workflows.</p>
<p>targets is not just another package; it’s a game-changer for reproducibility, efficiency, and scalability in your R projects. Developed to manage complex dependency graphs, targets automates the execution of your analyses, making it easier to track changes.</p>
<p>In this session we’ll introduce the targets package, discuss why it’s useful and explore the core features of the targets package by defining a basic pipeline.</p>
<section id="biography---simon-rolph" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="biography---simon-rolph">Biography - Simon Rolph</h3>
<p>Simon is a Data Scientist at the <a href="https://www.ceh.ac.uk/">UK Centre for Ecology and Hydrology</a> where he works to enhance our understanding of biodiversity and contribute to informed environmental decision-making. Technology is his enabler: data science methods, research software best practices, and digital engagements help him achieve these goals.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-02-15/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2024 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-02-15/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SheffieldR : January 2024 Meetup</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-01-18-jan-meetup/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>SheffieldR User Group is back in January 2024 with a Health Economics special and two talks from Robert Smith and Wael Mohammed of <a href="https://darkpeakanalytics.com/">Dark Peak Analytics</a> and the University of Sheffield who will talk us through two of their recent publications. Rob will show us how to automate Health Economic Evaluation with R without sharing sensitive data and Wael will guide us through a tutorial on R packaging for cost-effectiveness models.</p>
<p>Meeting is 2024-01-18 17:00-18:30 in The Diamond G04 Workroom 1. Sign up <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sheffieldr-sheffield-r-users-group/events/297758319/">here</a>. Remote attendance is possible using <a href="https://meet.google.com/iqv-jzvh-tow">Google Meet</a>.</p>
<p>If you have any questions or enquiries please get in touch with <a href="mailto:g.accad@sheffield.ac.uk">Grace Accad</a> or <a href="mailto:n.shephard@sheffield.ac.uk">Neil Shephard</a>.</p>
<!--more-->
<section id="robert-smith" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="robert-smith">Robert Smith</h2>
<p><a href="https://wellcomeopenresearch.org/articles/7-194">Living HTA: Automating Health Economic Evaluation with R</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://wellcomeopenresearch.s3.amazonaws.com/manuscripts/20423/08572b94-ad7b-437b-9f0f-874956e03474_figure1.gif" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Schematic showing the interaction between the company API (application programming interface) and the consultant automated workflow.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Background</strong>: Requiring access to sensitive data can be a significant obstacle for the development of health models in the Health Economics &amp; Outcomes Research (HEOR) setting. We demonstrate how health economic evaluation can be conducted with minimal transfer of data between parties, while automating reporting as new information becomes available.</p>
<p><strong>Methods</strong>: We developed an automated analysis and reporting pipeline for health economic modelling and made the source code openly available on a GitHub repository. The pipeline consists of three parts: An economic model is constructed by the consultant using pseudo data. On the data-owner side, an application programming interface (API) is hosted on a server. This API hosts all sensitive data, so that data does not have to be provided to the consultant. An automated workflow is created, which calls the API, retrieves results, and generates a report.</p>
<p><strong>Results</strong> : The application of modern data science tools and practices allows analyses of data without the need for direct access – negating the need to send sensitive data. In addition, the entire workflow can be largely automated: the analysis can be scheduled to run at defined time points (e.g.&nbsp;monthly), or when triggered by an event (e.g.&nbsp;an update to the underlying data or model code); results can be generated automatically and then be exported into a report. Documents no longer need to be revised manually.</p>
<p><strong>Conclusions</strong>: This example demonstrates that it is possible, within a HEOR setting, to separate the health economic model from the data, and automate the main steps of the analysis pipeline.</p>
<section id="biography---robert-smith" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="biography---robert-smith">Biography - Robert Smith</h3>
<p>Rob is a health economist based in Sheffield, UK. His research focuses on the methods used to estimate the costs and benefits of public health interventions, with a specific interest in microsimulation modelling in R. He is a expert advisor in Public Health Economics &amp; Decision Science to the WHO-HEAT project. He is currently working at the Joint Biosecurity Centre to help inform the UK government response to the pandemic.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="wael-mohammed" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wael-mohammed">Wael Mohammed</h2>
<p><a href="https://wellcomeopenresearch.org/articles/8-419">Packaging cost-effectiveness models in R: A Tutorial</a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://wellcomeopenresearch.s3.eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/manuscripts/21773/92d51709-7e6b-4167-903f-31d7ba03dc47_figure2.gif" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Schematic of a typical model structure taking raw data and user inputs and using a set of functions to return results in the form of data, publication tables, and figures.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Background</strong>: The use of programming languages such as R in health economics and decision science is increasing, and brings numerous benefits including increasing model development efficiency, improving transparency, and reducing human error. However, there is limited guidance on how to best develop models using R. So far, no clear consensus has emerged.</p>
<p><strong>Methods</strong>: We present the advantages of creating health economic models as R packages - structured collections of functions, data sets, tests, and documentation. Assuming an intermediate understanding of R, we provide a tutorial to demonstrate how to construct a basic R package for health economic evaluation. All source code used in or referenced by this paper is available under an open-source licence.</p>
<p><strong>Case Study</strong>: We use the Sick Sicker Model as a case study applying the steps from the tutorial to standardise model development, documentation and aid review. This can improve the distribution of code, thereby streamlining model development, and improving methods in health economic evaluation.</p>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong>: R packages offer a valuable framework for enhancing the quality and transparency of health economic evaluation models. Embracing better, more standardised software development practices, while fostering a collaborative culture, has the potential to significantly improve the quality of health economic models, and, ultimately, support better decision making in healthcare.</p>
<section id="biography---wael-mohammed" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="biography---wael-mohammed">Biography - Wael Mohammed</h3>
<p>Wael is a health economist with a background in pharmacy and public health. In addition, he has experience in decision-analytic modelling, econometrics, and data science. He is currently pursuing a PhD in public health, economics and decision science at the University of Sheffield.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-01-18-jan-meetup/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2024 17:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2024-01-18-jan-meetup/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="105" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SheffieldR : November Meetup</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2023-11-20-nov-meetup/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>After October’s Reboot, we are back with another Meetup this 20th November for a showcase using Shiny to illuminate the power of data-driven insights. Join us as we delve into the world of interactive data visualization, with hands-on demonstrations, insightful discussions, and practical use cases that will empower you to harness the potential of Shiny in your own projects.</p>
<p>Meeting is 2023-11-20 17:30-19:00 in 107 Workroom 4, 38 Mappin Street. Sign up <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sheffieldr-sheffield-r-users-group/events/297112060/">here</a>.</p>
<!--more-->
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2023-11-20-nov-meetup/image.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Sheffield LSOAs</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Join us for an exciting showcase where we’ll dive into two innovative R-Shiny projects. The first project introduces the fascinating world of mapping to investigate the dynamics of segregation among neighboring regions, a concept we fondly refer to as “social frontiers.” In the second project, we explore economic sectors with a focus on aiding South Yorkshire’s mayoral authority in their strategic growth planning endeavours.</p>
<p>The burning question that currently occupies our minds: How can we leverage powerful tools like Shiny to assist other institutions, including local councils and mayoral offices, in streamlining their data analysis processes and preventing unnecessary duplication of effort? Be a part of this engaging exploration and discover how Shiny can be a game-changer in data analysis for various institutions. Don’t miss this opportunity to be part of the conversation and gain valuable insights into the future of data-driven decision-making.</p>
<section id="biography" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="biography">Biography</h3>
<p>Dr Dan Olner is a policy fellow with Y-PERN, the <a href="https://www.sheffield.ac.uk/city-region/community-relations/yorkshire-humber-policy-engagement-research-network-y-pern">Yorkshire Policy Engagement and Research Network</a>, working closely with SMYCA in their business, growth and skills team on all things spatial, data and regional. His background is in spatial analysis, spatial economics, data science and politics. He has an interest in using data analysis to address sustainability and net zero issues. More info at <a href="https://danolner.net">Danoler</a>!</p>
<p>If you have any questions or inquires please get in touch with <a href="mailto:g.accad@sheffield.ac.uk">Grace Accad</a> or <a href="mailto:n.shephard@sheffield.ac.uk">Neil Shephard</a>/</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2023-11-20-nov-meetup/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2023-11-20-nov-meetup/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="118" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SheffieldR Reboot : Quarto for slides</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2023-10-26-oct-meetup/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>After a long hiatus SheffieldR User Group is back and we’ll be starting things off by looking at the new document preparation system <a href="https://quarto.org">Quarto</a> and how to use it with GitHub to publish presentations as websites. There is however still scope for a second talk so if you’d like to make a short presentation on how you have used R in your research please <a href="mailto:n.shephard@sheffield.ac.uk">get in touch</a>.</p>
<p>Meeting is 2023-10-26 17:30-19:00 in LT02 (60), Arts Tower, Western Bank, Sheffield. Sign up <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sheffieldr-sheffield-r-users-group/events/296493587/">here</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53182749103_d03f3bbd0a_k.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption><a href="https://flickr.com/photos/slackline/53182749103/"><em>Plants to Boot</em> Picture by Neil Shephard</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<!--more-->
<section id="introduction-to-plotly" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction-to-plotly">Introduction to Plotly</h2>
<p>Unlock the power of interactive and engaging data visualizations with <a href="https://plotly.com/r/">Plotly in R</a>! In this workshop, you’ll dive into the world of Plotly, a leading data visualization library, and learn how to create stunning, interactive charts and graphs for your data analysis projects.</p>
<p><a href="mailto:g.accad@sheffield.ac.uk">Grace Accad</a>, Data Scientist in the <a href="https://dataviz.shef.ac.uk/">Data Visualisation Team</a> at The University of Sheffield, will showcase the use of Plotly to enhance your graphics.</p>
</section>
<section id="quarto-for-revealjs-slides" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="quarto-for-revealjs-slides">Quarto for RevealJS Slides</h2>
<p>The evolution of literate programming continues with <a href="https://quarto.org">Quarto</a> which builds on the widely popular <a href="https://bookdown.org/yihui/rmarkdown/">RMarkdown</a>. Powered by <a href="https://pandoc.org/">Pandoc</a> under the hood it continues to provide many popular document structures such as books, journal articles, Beamer articles and websites, but extends these further introducing new document structures such as blogs and <a href="https://revealjs.com">RevealJS</a> slide presentations. Further support is now available for more programming languages beyond R including <a href="https://python.org">Python</a>, <a href="https://julialang.org">Julia</a> and the JavaScript data analysis language <a href="https://observablehq.com/@observablehq/observable-javascript">Observable</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.sheffield.ac.uk/dcs/people/research-staff/neil-shephard">Neil Shephard</a> is a <a href="https://rse.shef.ac.uk">Research Software Engineer</a> within the Department of Computer Science, will guide you through how to use a GitHub Template for Quarto RevealJS slides to create and publish them to <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a>.</p>
<p>You can view the slides that were presented <a href="https://ns-rse.github.io/SheffieldR-quarto-for-slides/">here</a> and if you wanted to try making slides yourself you can use the <a href="https://github.com/ns-rse/quarto-revealjs-template">Quarto RevealJS Template</a> that was demoed. The talk/slides cover the material that is on the front <code>README.md</code>. If you find any mistakes please do report an <a href="https://github.com/ns-rse/quarto-revealjs-template/issues">issue</a>.</p>
<section id="speaker-biography" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="speaker-biography">Speaker Biography</h3>
<p><a href="https://ns-rse.github.io">Neil</a> is a Research Software Engineer at the University of Sheffield. His career has been varied with time as a Genetic Epidemiologist, Medical Statistician working on Clinical Trials and time in industry working as a Data Scientist in a startup tech company. He combines his knowledge and experience to help researchers at the University of Sheffield improve the quality and openness of their code and data.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2023-10-26-oct-meetup/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/53182749103_d03f3bbd0a_k.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>rrtools: Tools for Writing Reproducible Research in R</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2018-04-10-apr-meetup/2018-04-10-apr-meetup.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>NOTE: Because of the Easter holidays April’s meetup will be on the 2nd Tue of the month.</em></p>
<p>This month we’ll be exploring <strong>rrtools</strong>, an implementation of R package structure, development tools and practices to a research workflow context.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Rrtools builds on functionality offered by packages like devtools and usethis, adapting and extending them to a research context. The package provides guidance, templates, and functions for making a basic compendium suitable for doing reproducible research with R and a convenient starting point for writing a journal article, report, or thesis.</p>
<p><em>Useful features:</em></p>
<ul>
<li><p>A template for doing scholarly writing in a literate programming environment using <a href="http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/">R Markdown</a> and <a href="https://bookdown.org/home/about.html">bookdown</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Isolation of your computational environment in a container using <a href="https://www.docker.com/what-docker">Docker</a></p></li>
<li><p>Package dependency versioning using <a href="https://mran.microsoft.com/documents/rro/reproducibility/">MRAN</a>,</p></li>
<li><p>Continuous Integration (testing) using <a href="https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/for-beginners">Travis</a>.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>In this joint session, Anna Krystalli will give an overview of the philosophy, key functions and resulting compendium structure while Dan Olner will walk us through using the tools to convert an existing research project to a reproducible research compendium.</p>
<section id="speaker-bio" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="speaker-bio">Speaker Bio</h2>
<p><a href="http://danolner.github.io/">Dan</a> is a researcher in the Sheffield Methods Institute working on a diverse bunch of projects, from modelling whether houses can see wind turbines or green space to making 3D prints of Census data to making monsters using a Kinect motion sensor. He also occasionally runs day workshops on data wrangling and visualisation in R.</p>
<p><a href="http://annakrystalli.me/">Anna</a> is a Research Software Engineer at the University of Sheffield, helping researchers do more with their code and data.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2018-04-10-apr-meetup/2018-04-10-apr-meetup.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Docker and Interactive unit testing</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2018-03-06-mar-meetup/2018-03-06-mar-meetup.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In this month’s meetup, Mark Dunning will give a general introduction to the Docker container platform and Phil Mike Jones will introduce strategies for interactive unit testing.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Mark Dunning (<a href="https://twitter.com/DrMarkDunning"><span class="citation" data-cites="DrMarkDunning">@DrMarkDunning</span></a>) will give a general introduction to the Docker container platform and present a couple of R-related examples in which he used it to distribute course materials and supplementary materials for a paper. Mark joined Sheffield University in October 2017 to set up a Bioinformatics Core facility, having previously worked for Cancer Research UK in Cambridge after completing his PhD. The <a href="http://sbc.shef.ac.uk">Sheffield Bioinformatics Core</a> provides support on the analysis and interpretation of biological datasets as well as a programme of training courses. Mark is an R and open-science enthusiast and has contributed software to the popular Bioconductor project and developed and delivered numerous training courses on R.</p>
<p>Phil Mike Jones (<a href="https://twitter.com/philmikejones"><span class="citation" data-cites="philmikejones">@philmikejones</span></a>) will talk us through some interactive unit testing using examples from his package, <a href="https://github.com/philmikejones/rakeR/tree/master/tests">rakeR</a>, and his reproducible <a href="https://github.com/philmikejones/thesis/tree/master/data-raw">PhD thesis</a>. Phil is a research associate in the Centre for Criminological Research based in the School of Law at the University of Sheffield, working on the “Long-term impacts of ‘Thatcherism’: crime, politics and inequality” project. He has just finished a PhD in human geography at the University of Sheffield, entitled ‘A Spatial Microsimulation Analysis of Health Inequalities and Health Resilience’.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2018-03-06-mar-meetup/2018-03-06-mar-meetup.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2018 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Stan and the Tidyverse</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2018-02-06-feb-meetup/2018-02-06-feb-meetup.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Welcome back to the Sheffield R Meetup! We’re kicking off 2018 with two great talks:</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Shaun Coutts will be giving a demonstration of using Stan via the <a href="https://mc-stan.org/users/interfaces/rstan">rstan</a> interface and launching jobs on iceberg and sharc.</p>
<p>Katjuša Koler will be talking about doing things differently using the Tidyverse:</p>
<p>In this session, I will give an example of a workflow in base R and compare it to a tidyverse approach. Tidyverse is a system of packages (dplyr, ggplot2 etc.) used to manipulate, explore and visualize data. I will discuss the pros and cons of each workflow. This talk will be useful for beginners, as well as anyone considering making a bridge from base R to tidyverse.</p>
<p>So two talks, one with Bayes R and one with Base R! We look forward to seeing you there.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2018-02-06-feb-meetup/2018-02-06-feb-meetup.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>R coding social</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2017-12-05-dec-meetup/2017-12-05-dec-meetup.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In the run up to the festive season we’d like to invite Sheffield R users to come and join us for an R coding social! Come along for a chance to meet and greet fellow R users in Sheffield. If you have a coding problem to discuss, feel free to bring it along and take advantage of the wealth of R coding knowledge available!</p>
<!--more-->
<p>We’ll start with a round of introductions, allowing people briefly to introduce themselves. After going around the room, there will be the opportunity for attendees to share code they’ve been working on and want help with / want feedback on / want to present.</p>
<p>Come with a topic you want to discuss or with something you’ve done that you want to tell everyone about, or just come to listen and contribute as much or as little as you want.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2017-12-05-dec-meetup/2017-12-05-dec-meetup.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2017 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Managing projects with workflowr and Introduction to DiagrammeR</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2017-11-07-nov-meetup/2017-11-07-nov-meetup.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We’re back to our regular schedule after last month’s Hacktoberfest fun. Join us for talks on managing your projects with workflowr and a brief introduction to the visualisation tool, DiagrammeR.</p>
<!--more-->
<section id="managing-projects-with-workflow" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="managing-projects-with-workflow">Managing projects with workflow</h2>
<p>In this session I’ll do a walk through of using package <a href="https://jdblischak.github.io/workflowr/">workflowr</a> to organise and document projects including some best practice tips and tricks.</p>
<p>Anna Krystalli has a background in marine macroecology. Now she works as a Research Software Engineer at the University of Sheffield, helping researchers do more with their code and data.</p>
</section>
<section id="introduction-to-diagrammer" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction-to-diagrammer">Introduction to DiagrammeR</h2>
<p>In this session I’ll give a brief introduction to <a href="http://rich-iannone.github.io/DiagrammeR/">DiagrammeR</a>, a package for creating and visualising network graphs and diagrams, with built-in support for a range of formats. I’ll demonstrate how to create a data-driven network diagram using data on trade in endangered species.</p>
<p>Tamora James is a PhD researcher in the Department of Animal and Plant Sciences at the University of Sheffield. Her work involves modelling populations of vulnerable bird species to determine effective conservation interventions.</p>
</section>
<section id="sheffield-r-users-group-needs-you" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sheffield-r-users-group-needs-you">Sheffield R Users Group needs you</h2>
<p>We rely on members of the Sheffield R community to speak at our meetups and try to offer a mix of “beginners” and “expert” level talks. If you’d like to share a 15 minute informal slide-talk on a topic of your choosing (broadly ‘something cool I’ve done related to R that others would benefit from hearing about’) then we’d love to hear from you!</p>
<p>Let us know by filling in our speaker <a href="https://goo.gl/forms/6EQaWs7PsxdOP04l2">sign up form</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2017-11-07-nov-meetup/2017-11-07-nov-meetup.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Celebrating Hacktoberfest… #rstats style!</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2017-10-03-oct-meetup/2017-10-03-oct-meetup.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We’ll be following up our introductory <strong>Celebrating Hacktoberfest</strong> session with drop-in sessions throughout October, so do join us if you’d like to get involved or learn more about open source!</p>
<section id="schedule-for-the-rest-of-the-month" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="schedule-for-the-rest-of-the-month">Schedule for the rest of the month</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Tu Oct 10 5:00 pm - 8:00 pm</strong> University of Sheffield, Diamond Meeting room 1</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Tu Oct 17 5:30 pm - 8:30 pm</strong> University of Sheffield, Information Commons Collaboratory 1 ‐ 1.26</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Tu Oct 24 5:30 pm - 8:30 pm</strong> University of Sheffield, Diamond Meeting room 1</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Tu Oct 31 5:30 pm - 8:30 pm</strong> University of Sheffield, Diamond Meeting room 1 - <strong>Halloween Hacktoberfest!</strong></p></li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://cloud.githubusercontent.com/assets/121322/18864038/31532b4a-8449-11e6-8701-97c00c95bf09.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Hacktoberfest banner</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<!--more-->
<p>It’s <a href="https://hacktoberfest.digitalocean.com/">Hacktoberfest</a> over on GitHub! a global celebration of open source intended to promote participation in open source projects.</p>
<p>So this month we’re taking a break from talks and booked some group hackspaces at the University throughout the month to <strong>get involved in some open source projects requiring some #rstats help.</strong></p>
<p>Anyone can benefit from getting involved, regardless of coding skill. At the very least, you’ll <strong>learn more about open source</strong> and <strong>how to contribute through online collaborative coding platforms like GitHub</strong>. But you never know, you might end up stumbling across the perfect project for you and ending up joining a community.</p>
<p>You can choose to contribute as little or much as you like, from correcting typos, contributing ideas to discussions to building features! Make at least 4 contributions (pull requests) to any GitHub-hosted project between October 1 and October 31 to <strong>earn a limited edition Hacktoberfest T-shirt!</strong></p>
</section>
<section id="at-todays-meetup" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="at-todays-meetup">At today’s meetup</h2>
<p>We’ll take a look at <a href="https://github.com/search?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;q=label%3Ahacktoberfest+state%3Aopen+type%3Aissue+language%3AR&amp;type=">Hacktoberfest R projects on GitHub</a> (many <a href="https://ropensci.org/">rOpenSci</a> packages requiring help!) and discuss how to use GitHub to contribute to projects e.g.&nbsp;how to make a pull request, best practice for contributing code etc.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2017-10-03-oct-meetup/2017-10-03-oct-meetup.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2017 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>September Sheffield R Meetup: Object oriented systems in R + The Reproducible Thesis w/ Bookdown</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2017-09-05-sept-meetup/2017-09-05-sept-meetup.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="welcome-back-to-a-new-season-of-r-user-group-meetups" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="welcome-back-to-a-new-season-of-r-user-group-meetups">Welcome back to a new season of R user group meetups</h2>
<p>We’ve got an exciting pair of talks for you this month!</p>
<!--more-->
<p>First up, <strong>Chris Hopkinson</strong>, self-described Data Lover, will be talking us through <strong>Object oriented systems in R</strong>:</p>
<p><em>“Object Oriented programming is commonplace in many languages. It is a useful way to organise code. R has some special flavours of Object Oriented programming. Understanding these will help you understand R better and write better software.”</em></p>
<p>Then, we have <strong>Phil Mike Jones</strong>, a geographer about to complete his PhD in computational human geography + a research associate at the Centre for Criminological Research at the School of Law,who will be discussing his journey in writing a <strong>Reproducible Thesis with Bookdown</strong>.</p>
<p><em>“My PhD thesis is completely reproducible (except a few items that cannot be downloaded without website credentials) and this has saved me no end of headaches now I’m preparing to submit. Supervisor (or boss) asked for some changes? No problem: change the data, run the code, and sit back as all figures and calculations are automatically updated. I probably don’t need to remind you that reproducibility is also the hallmark of the scientific method.</em></p>
<p><em>In this session, I’ll share some tips that I discovered along the way and hopefully, at least some will be helpful for your projects. A completely reproducible project might not be possible or practical for you, but reproducibility is a scale so all projects could benefit from at least some of this advice.”</em></p>
<p>Hope to see you there.</p>
<p>The SheffieldR team</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2017-09-05-sept-meetup/2017-09-05-sept-meetup.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>July Sheffield R Meetup: Thermal images and Object oriented systems in R</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2017-07-04-july-meetup/2017-07-04-july-meetup.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We’ve got two great talks lined up for our last meeting before the summer break.</p>
<p><em>Update: Due to a change in availability we have had to postpone the talk on object oriented systems in R. Instead we’ll be holding an informal code clinic, so come along with any coding problems that you want to discuss.</em></p>
<p><strong>Rebecca Senior</strong> is a 3rd year PhD student in the Department of Animal and Plant Sciences at the University of Sheffield, and avid lover of using R to do just about everything! She studies interactions between land-use change and climate change in the tropics. She’s going to talk about the work she’s been doing analysing thermal image data collected in the forests of Borneo.</p>
<p><strong>Chris Hopkinson</strong> is a Sheffield R group regular, analyst and data lover. He’ll be giving us the low-down on object oriented systems in R.</p>
<!--more-->
<section id="thermal-images-in-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thermal-images-in-r">Thermal images in R</h2>
<p>Rebecca will introduce the ThermImage package and demonstrate its use in extracting and processing thermal images in R. She’ll talk about the challenges associated with the structure of thermal data and the kinds of questions that ecologists can ask with such data, such as capturing the extent to which animals can move locally to track their preferred temperatures. A single thermal image produces 19,200 distinct temperature measurements, so optimising the extraction -&gt; processing -&gt; plotting -&gt; analysis workflow is essential.</p>
</section>
<section id="object-oriented-systems-in-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="object-oriented-systems-in-r">Object oriented systems in R</h2>
<p>Object Oriented programming is commonplace in many languages. It is a useful way to organise code. R has some special flavours of Object Oriented programming. Understanding these will help you understand R better and write better software.</p>
<p>We hope to see you there!</p>
<p>The SheffieldR team</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2017-07-04-july-meetup/2017-07-04-july-meetup.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2017 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>June Sheffield R Meetup: Literate programming and Writing a decision tree package for R</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2017-06-06-june-meetup/2017-06-06-june-meetup.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This month Anna Krystalli will present a exploration of literate programming, following up from a discussion on literate programming techniques at our meetup in April, and Pete Dodd will tell us about building an open source decision tree package in R.</p>
<section id="literate-programming-with-rmarkdown" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="literate-programming-with-rmarkdown">Literate programming with Rmarkdown</h2>
<p>In this session we’ll explore the various options and strategies for literate programming and dynamic report generation in R and Rmarkdown. This session will make use of the literate programming packages knitr and Rmarkdown.</p>
</section>
<section id="writing-a-decision-tree-package-for-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="writing-a-decision-tree-package-for-r">Writing a decision tree package for R</h2>
<p>Decision trees are a class of model widely used in health economic modelling. A tree (in the mathematical sense) has probabilities associated with branches leaving a node to describe the chances of a set of potential outcomes. In health economics, costs and health consequences are also associated with outcomes. By way of example, clinical diagnostic algorithms based on a sequence of symptom screens and diagnostic tests map particularly naturally into this framework. There are proprietary packages to develop, visualize and analyse such models, but nothing open-source and user-friendly. We describe an attempt to develop a package with a simple syntax for decision tree models in R based on the DOT language, which allows visualization, as well as considerable flexibility in analysis approach.</p>
<p>We hope to see you there!</p>
<p>The SheffieldR team</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2017-06-06-june-meetup/2017-06-06-june-meetup.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2017 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>May Sheffield R Meetup: Making R Faster</title>
  <link>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2017-05-02-may-meetup/2017-05-02-may-meetup.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This month we’ll be learning from Théo Michelot how to make R go faster using a couple of techniques.</p>
<section id="using-c-to-speed-up-r-code" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="using-c-to-speed-up-r-code">Using C++ to speed up R code</h2>
<p>R is a very handy tool for data analysis, but it can be computationally quite slow. When analysing large data sets, or using complex models, it can be desirable to speed things up. For this reason, it has become increasingly common to combine R code with C++ code. C++ is a compiled programming language, which makes it much faster than R in some cases. I will first talk about Rcpp, an R package which makes it very simple to call C++ functions from an R script. Then, I will talk about the Template Model Builder (TMB), an R package which uses automatic differentiation in C++ to speed up the numerical evaluation of a function (typically, a likelihood function), thus making techniques such as maximum likelihood estimation very fast. I will show that these do not require a strong programming background, and that it is quite easy for someone familiar with R to use Rcpp and TMB. I will compare the three approaches with examples of code.</p>
<p>We hope to see you there!</p>
<p>The SheffieldR team</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>meetups</category>
  <guid>https://SheffieldR.github.io/posts/2017-05-02-may-meetup/2017-05-02-may-meetup.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
